From
từ
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
[Laughter]
[Tiếng cười]
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
In the time when the Buddha resided at the Jetavana Monastery,
thuở sư Đức Phật trú tại tinh xá Kỳ Hoàn
water was cheap because of the gods, people, officials, and the common
nước giá rẻ vì hàng trời người vu quan
people. He preached the Wonderful Dharma. At that time,
dân chúng Tuyên thuyết Diệu Pháp lúc ấy
along the road, there was a
bên đường có một gia đình Trưởng giả
wealthy family of the Brahmin family. They had a
Phạm Chí giàu có vô số chỉ Sinh được một
son who was now 20 years old. The old
trai năm nay vừa tròn 20 tuổi
man had just married his son off seven
ông chở già mới cưới vợ cho con được 7
days earlier. The couple loved each other and lived
ngày hai vợ chồng yêu thương ăn ở thuận
harmoniously. The wife told her husband she wanted to
hòa với nhau người vợ nói với chồng muốn
go to the backyard to admire the scenery and enjoy the flowers. The
ra vườn sau ngắm cảnh thưởng hoa chồng
husband indulged her, and they went to the backyard. It was springtime,
chiều ý vợ hai người đưa nhau ra vườn
and in the
sau lúc này đương và viết xuân trong
garden, there was a tree in a beautiful spot.
vườn có một cây lại ở chỗ qua tươi đẹp
The wife wanted to pick flowers, but there were no flowers. The husband, not wanting to
Vợ muốn hái hoa xong không có người
disappoint his wife, climbed the tree to pick them. He swung
chồng hết ý vợ liền trèo lên cây hái
from branch to branch
người chồng treo từ cành này sang cành
to pick flowers, but unexpectedly, he hit a
khác để hái hoa không ngờ Đạt nhằm càng
small branch, broke it, and fell to his death. The whole family, hearing the
nhỏ gãy rơi xuống chết liền cả nhà hay
news, rushed to embrace their son's body, weeping and wailing until they fainted. When they regained consciousness,
tin vội chạy đến ôm xác con than khóc
relatives from inside and
đến ngất đi tỉnh lại thân tộc trong
outside the family came to visit in large numbers, all extremely
ngoài đến thăm đông đảo ai cũng hết sức
saddened. Those who heard the story felt sorrowful and shed tears.
thương tâm Người nghe xót xa kể thấy rơi
The parents blamed heaven for its cruelty. Afterwards,
lệ cha mẹ trách trời sao tàn nhẫn sau đó
everyone prepared the body and took him to be
mọi người tẩn liệm rồi đem anh đi chôn
buried. Upon returning home, the whole family wept all day long.
cất khi trở về cả nhà suốt ngày than
Now...  The Buddha,
khóc mãi không thôi bây giờ Đức Thế Tôn
moved by their ignorance,
thương cho sự ngu muội của họ nên đến
visited the old man's family. Seeing the Buddha, the old man
thăm hỏi cả nhà trưởng già thấy Phật đến
wept in sorrow and recounted his story.
đau buồn khóc lóc anh đem hết sự tình ra
The Buddha said to the old man, "Please stop
kể lể Đức Phật bảo với trưởng già Xin
weeping. Listen to me. All
Đừng than khóc nữa hãy nghe ta nói Vạn
things are impermanent; nothing lasts forever. What
vật đều vô thường không thể trường Cửu
is born must die. Merit and demerit follow one another.
đã sinh thì phải tử Tội Phước theo nhau
This child truly has three reasons for
đứa con này thật ra có đến ba chỗ phải
weeping; the sorrow and grief are
thằng khóc vì nó sự đau buồn hay nơi kia
nothing to worry about. Ultimately, whose child is he?
cũng không sao Cẩm nổi nó Rốt cuộc là
Who is his relative
con ai ai là người thân của nó
now?" The Buddha then recited a verse: "
bây giờ Đức Thế Tôn liền nói kệ
Life is like a ripe fruit; its use is fleeting.
mạng sống như trái chín xét dụng chẳng
Born into suffering, no one is immortal.
bao lâu đã sinh là phải khổ ai bất tử
Because of past desires, lust, and lustful thoughts, the body
được đâu do trước tham ái dục tưởng dâm
enters the womb, satisfying the mind, strong as lightning,
nhập bào thai thỏa thân mạnh như điện
constantly watching day and night. The body
ngày đêm luôn dòm hoài
is a dying thing, the spirit transcends the path.
thân ngài là vật chết tinh thần vượt phố
When death awakens, rebirth occurs. Merit and demerit are not
khi thần chết thức tái sinh Tội Phước
lost;
vẫn không mất
before and after countless lifetimes, due to prolonged attachment and delusion,
trước sau biết bao đời do Ái si kéo dài
suffering and joy are created by oneself. When death comes, the spirit remains." After
khổ vui tự mình tạo thân chết thần còn
hearing the story, the old man suddenly
lại trường già Nghe kể xong chợt thông
understood. Still sorrowful, he clasped his hands and waved his hand dismissively.
hiểu không Còn đau buồn vì thẳng chắp
The Buddha asked, "
tay bạch phẩy phẩy nước Thế Tôn Người
What sins did this child commit in his previous life that he must die so young in this life?" The Buddha then told the old man, "What sins did this child commit in his previous life that he must die
con này đời trước gây tội gì mà Đời Nay
so young in this life?"  In a
phải yểu mạng như vậy sinh ngày rảnh nói
past life, there was a child who brought a bow and arrow to
quá khứ có một đứa bé mang cung tên đến
a sacred tree to play. Three
một cây thần chơi bên cạnh đó cũng có 3
other people were nearby. Seeing a sparrow on the tree,
người nữa thấy trên cây có con chim sẻ
the child wanted to shoot it. The three people encouraged him, saying that if he hit the
đứa bé muốn bắn ba người kia thấy vậy
sparrow, he would be a
khuyến khích bắn trúng được con chim sẻ
true hero. The child was
đó mới thật là bậc Tiểu Anh Hùng Đứa Bé
so pleased that he shot the sparrow. The arrow
em thích quá liền Dương cũng bắn chim sẻ
fell to the ground and the sparrow died. The three people
chúng tên rơi xuống đất chết ba người
praised him and left. Through countless
kia khen nhờ rồi bỏ đi trải qua vô số
lifetimes of birth and death, they met again
kiếp người trong sinh tử họ lại gặp gỡ
and shared the same karma. One of them was
và cùng Thọ tội một người trong bọn có
fortunate enough to be reborn in heaven, another was reborn as a
phước này ở cõi trời một người hóa sinh
Dragon King in the underworld, and the third
làm Long Vương ở dưới miền còn một người
was an old man. The child who shot the
là Thanh Trưởng già đứa bé cẩm tên bắn
sparrow was his son. In a previous life,
chim chính là con ông ngày nay đời trước
he was born as the son of a wealthy man, and by divine will, he was reborn as the
nó sinh làm con của người ở có ý trời
son of a wealthy man.
rồi mạc chung sinh làm con của Trưởng
Now, having fallen and died, he is reborn as the son
Giả giờ đây nó té chết lại sinh làm con
of a Dragon King in the sea. He
của người làm long vương dưới biển thế
will be eaten by the Golden-Winged Bird King as soon as he is born.
này nó vừa sinh ra sẽ bị kim sí điểu
Today, the three people
Vương ăn thịt ngày nay bọn ông Ba người
in three different places are grieving and weeping for the child
ở 3 nơi đều vì đứa nhỏ mà buồn khổ than
because they encouraged him to
khóc do vì các ông đã tán trợ đứa bé
kill the sparrow, and therefore must suffer the painful retribution of weeping and
giết chim nên phải chịu báo ứng khổ đau
lamenting. Now, the Buddha recited a
than khóc bây giờ Đức Thế Tôn liền nói
verse to awaken the mind and create the three girls.  Good and
kệ thức Tâm Tạo ba cô ấy 5 chỗ Thiện bất
evil deeds are done secretly, leading to the same destination as
thiện thầm làm thầm đưa đến chỗ đến như
the echoes of the formless and formless realms. All are due to the consequences of
tiếng vang dục sắc vô sắc giới Tất cả do
good deeds, like seeds bearing fruit,
tốt nghiệp như giống nào trái nấy báo
like shadows following the form. After the Buddha finished speaking,
như bóng theo hình Đức Phật nói kể xong
wanting to bring about enlightenment, he
muốn khiến trưởng giờ giác ngộ nên đã
used his supernatural powers to make everyone see
dùng thần thông khiến cho mọi người thấy
the events happening in the heavenly realms. The
túc mạ những việc xảy ra ở cõi trời Loài
long-tailed dragons, upon hearing this, joyfully rose and knelt
rồng trường giả nghe xong hoan hỷ đứng
down, clasping their hands and
dậy ra anh thật Quỳ Xuống chắp tay bạch
respectfully asking the Buddha to allow their entire family to become his
xin đức thế tôn cho cả nhà chúng con làm
disciples, to observe the Five Precepts, and to become lay followers. The
đệ tử thỏ chỉ Ngũ giới làm cư sĩ tại gia
Buddha promised to impart the Five Precepts to
Đức Phật hứa cả truyền trao ngũ giới cho
them, then preached the Dharma on the meaning of impermanence.
họ rồi lại thuyết pháp về nghĩa Vô
Everyone rejoiced and attained the fruit of
Thường mọi người hoan hỷ Đắc quả
Stream-Enterer.
tu-đà-hoàn à
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
Yes, yes
ừ ừ